Preliminary Inventory to the Sidney Percy Marland Papers, 1943-1991
Hoover Institution Archives
Sidney Percy Marland Papers
1943-1991
79046
Hoover Institution Archives
35 manuscript boxes 14.6 linear feet
Speeches and writings, reports, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs, relating to education in the United States, governmental educational policy, and the career education movement.
Marland, Sidney Percy
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biography
American educator; United States commissioner of education, 1970- 1972; assistant secretary of health, education and welfare, 1972- 1973.
Scope and Contents note
Speeches and writings, reports, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs, relating to education in the United States, governmental educational policy, and the career education movement.
United States. Dept. of Health, Education and Welfare.; United States. Office of Education.; Education--United States.; Education.; Teachers--United States.; United States--Politics and government.
- Health, Education and Welfare. This material consists of selected documents associated with my period as U.S. Commissioner of Education, and Assistant Secretary of H.E.W, 1972-1973. This bundle does not include material on career education, which is assembled separately, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Task Force report (under my direction) pertaining to Financing Higher Education. This led to the so-called bench-mark legislation of and Basic Educational Opportunity Grants at the multi-billion dollar level, 1972
  - Clippings on nomination to U.S. Commissioner post, and details of disputes with the AFL/CIO over my appointment. See also Pittsburgh material on this, including letter to faculty from Mrs. M. C. Aaron, 1970
  - Testimony before Congress, chronologically assembled, 1970-1972
  - Selected statements by Sidney Percy Marland, to O. E. staff, Congress, the public, etc., 1971-1972
  - Other selected statements, including exchanges with the White House, 1970-1973
  - Analytical and Critical study of Educational Renewal, a proposal by Sidney Percy Marland, with support of the White House, which foundered badly in Congress, for reason of political disfavor toward any initiative by Republican Executive Branch (Box 2)
  - "Quoting Marland" in American Education, and other publications, 1971
  - Miscellaneous photos
  - Selected letters, pertaining to H.E.W responsibilities, etc.
- Superintendent of Schools (Darien, Winnetka, Pittsburgh)
  - Selected letters, some key issues, three superintendency positions, 1948-1968
  - Transition, Winnetka to Pittsburgh, 1963
  - Publications, Winnetka period, 1956-1963
  - Military: correspondence, 43rd Infantry Division, Clipping of Citation, Distinguished Service Cross (cannot locate the other citations or decorations)
  - Miscellaneous, H.E.W period, Model, public affairs procedures, U.S.O.E., 1971, 1971-1973.
  - Several captioned photographs and personal letter from my secretary, Gertrude O'Hare, upon leaving employment in H.E.W.
- Superintendent of Schools (Darien, Winnetka, Pittsburgh) (Box 3)
  - List of speeches, articles, testimony, etc. totaling 240 items, (most of the written documents, as distinct from the interviews, are probably on file in U.S.O.E.), 1970-1973
  - Record of Oral History statement for LBJ Library, 1972 February
  - Job offers, general
- Career Education
  - Documents (H.E.W. and O. E.) pertaining to origin of career Education "movement," under Sidney Percy Marland as U.S. Commissioner of Education, 1971-1972
  - More of above, with emphasis on NIE role, when Sidney Percy Marland became Assistant Secretary under new law (Educational Amendments of N.I.E and U.S.O.E. were made parallel under Assistant Secretary, 1972).
  - Statement requested by President Nixon for major Executive initiative on Career Education (basis for a topic in State of the Union message, 1972-1973)
  - Examples of impact of Career Education on various levels of instruction - e.g. New York City Elementary and secondary Schools, Chatham College, U.S. Chamber of Commerce, etc. (Box 4)
  - Collection of manuscripts, commissioned by Sydney Percy Marland, as first systematic approach to Career Education as a federal initiative (published in paperback, 1972)
  - Selected publications on Career Education, some by Sydney Percy Marland, others by key observers of the "movement"
- Miscellaneous writings by Sidney Percy Marland, 1973-1978
  - Annual meeting messages from the President of College Board
  - Selected writings by Sydney Percy Marland as President of College Board (Box 5)
- Three black binders of official correspondence (some semi-official, as U.S. Commissioner of Education and Assistant Secretary, H.E.W., 1970-1973) (Box 5-6.)
  - Speeches, mostly as Superintendent of Schools, Darien (more to follow in separate shipment), 1948-1956 (Box 6)
  - Annual reports and other publications as Superintendent of Schools, Darien, and Winnetka, 1948-1956 (Box 7)
- Incremental materials (Box 8-35)